John, what do you say to people from
the, you know, current and former
intelligence community, people that call
you a trader? What do you say to them?
>> Nobody calls me a trader.
>> No.
>> In all ser in all seriousness, my
detractors are all either dead or
retired.
And this new generation at the agency
acknowledges me as a whistleblower.
Dozens of them have reached out to me
for advice. And listen, I said from the
very beginning, I was on the right side
of history. [music]
Bad decisions,
bad decisions, [music]
bad decisions.
>> Welcome back to the Bad Decisions
podcast, where we lead not with
celebrity, but with story. John Kiryaku
was recruited into the CIA by a graduate
school professor and spent his first
eight years as a Middle East analyst
specializing in Iraq. Following 9/11, he
was named chief of counterterrorism
operations in Pakistan, where he led
raids on al-Qaeda safe houses and
captured Abu Zuba in March 2002.
John worked at the CIA from 1990 to 2004
and received numerous awards, including
10 exceptional performance awards.
CIA officials offered to train Jon in
enhanced interrogation techniques, but
he refused. After leaving the agency,
John became the first US official to
publicly confirm water boarding was used
and called it torture. John Kuryaku,
welcome to the show.
>> Thanks so much for having me. Good to be
with you.
>> Thank you. So, let's I always like to
start with origin stories. Walk us
through how your professor recruited you
into the CIA. What was that conversation
like and when did you realize this was
serious?
>> Well, I was taking a grad school course
at George Washington University called
the psychology of leadership
and um it was taught by uh Dr. Gerald
Post, an eminent psychiatrist, author of
dozens of books on the mostly on the
psychology of terrorists.
And so, uh, he gave us an assignment
where we had to shadow our bosses for a
week and then write a psychological
profile of our bosses. And, uh, I was
working at a labor union in Washington
at the time called the United Food and
Commercial Workers Union. And I worked
for a guy that I was actually a little
bit afraid of. He was just a big mean,
loud, old school union organizer.
And um partway through the week uh we
had an argument and I uh I called him a
racist, which he was.
>> Mhm.
>> And he he balled up his hands to his
fists to to punch me. I put up my hands
to block what I thought would be the
inevitable, you know, punch to the face.
And then he shouted that his penis was
bigger than mine. And I quit on the
spot. I said, "You know what? You're
nuts. I quit." and I walked. So I wrote
my paper and it it's not just, you know,
John telling the story of how he quit.
It was this was a serious psychological
profile. We had done a lot of reading
and um and so it was very heavily
footnoted. I submitted the paper to Dr.
Post and a week later he sent it back to
me. He gave me an A and he wrote in the
margin, "Please see me after class." So
I went to see him after class. He closed
the office door and he said, "Look, I'm
not really a professor here. I'm a CIA
officer undercover as a professor here,
and I'm looking for people who might fit
into the CIA's culture. I think you
would fit into the CIA's culture. Would
you like to be a CIA officer?"
And I had a second to think about it and
I said, "Sure, yeah, I would. I wanted
to I wanted to go into public service. I
wanted to see the world and you just
kind of laid it there in front of me.
>> How interesting. Um
>> I should add that's illegal now. You
can't do that.
>> You can't recruit students or you can't
uh uh recruit people from the private
sector or what?
>> No, no, no. You can do both. You can't
do it secretly behind the scenes. We
have something since 1993 called the
Equal Employment Opportunity Act. So the
the playing field has to be level. It
can't just be one, you know, white guy
choosing other white guys behind closed
doors to to, you know, go to the CIA.
And so it's far less sexy. You have to
go to a recruiter on a college campus or
you have to go to www.cia.gov
and click apply. It's far less sexy now.
>> Interesting. John, you've said in the
past that the CIA looks for candidates
who have psychopathic tendencies but not
actually psychopaths. What's the
distinction?
>> Sociopathic.
>> Oh, sociopathic tendencies. Okay. Sorry.
What's the distinction between a
sociopathic tendencies and and a
sociopath?
>> Sure. Sociopath is someone who's unable
to feel remorse or guilt, just unable.
And usually those people, if they can
keep the the sort of criminal element of
it in check, they actually usually rise
up to the tops of their of their careers
as CEOs and COOs because they're
comfortable doing it on the backs of the
people around them. People who have
sociopathic tendencies
do have consciences. They do feel regret
and remorse. they do feel empathy, but
they are willing to break the law or
bend the law if they believe it's for
the, you know, greater good. And so
I was perfectly happy to break into
somebody's house and plant a bug or
install a camera if I believed that that
was a terrorist. I was perfectly happy
to break laws and, you know, commit
espionage while I was overseas.
But I'm a believer in the rule of law in
the United States and torture is
illegal. It's always been illegal, at
least since the since the Second World
War. And and that's where I drew the
line.
>> It's very interesting stuff. Um,
you know, there there seems to it it
seems the job does seem to require a bit
of moral flexibility.
Um,
>> sure. So
what was it about? And so Abu Zubeda was
was waterboarded what 80s something
times.
>> Yeah. 83 times.
>> And you concluded that uh that that
enhanced interrogation doesn't work. But
but uh but I've read that that that what
good intel did come out of him.
>> Oh yeah. Great intel came out of him.
Not not as a result of the
waterboarding.
>> Break it down.
>> I say this all the time. I Yeah, I I say
this all the time that it's it's like a
kick in my gut to compliment the FBI. It
really is. But interrogation is
something that the FBI is really good at
and they've always been good at it.
They've been interrogating prisoners
professionally since the Nuremberg
trials. And the way they do it is they
establish a rapport with the subject.
They establish a relationship. Sometimes
it takes days, maybe weeks, maybe
months, who knows? But eventually
the subject is going to open up. And Ali
Sufan, an FBI agent who was
interrogating Abu Zabeda, got him to
open up. And he gave us a couple of
things that were
dramatic in their helpfulness. Number
one, for the very first time, he gave us
the al-Qaeda wiring diagram. We had no
idea what al-Qaeda looked like as an
organization. We knew Osama bin Laden
was the number one. I zawahi was the
number two. The number three was, you
know, a little more gray. And then we
didn't have any idea what the rest of it
looked like. And Abu Zubeda gave us
that. We we were able to to disrupt
future attacks because Ali Sufan was
able to get this from Abu Zuba just in
the course of a conversation.
The other thing that Abu Zuba gave us
was the name Khaled Shikh Muhammad. We
had never heard the name before. We knew
that there was a very bad guy out there
using the Nom Dear Mkhtar.
We knew that Mkhtar was planning
terrible catastrophic terrorist attacks.
We had no idea what his real name was.
And then when Abu Zubed told us it was
Khaled Shake Muhammad, we had never
heard of the guy. Uh the problem with
torture techniques is that sure
eventually the the subject of the
torture is going to give up the
information that you want. that he's
going to tell you so much about so many
things, most of it being nonsense, just
to get you to stop torturing him.
>> Stop hurting him.
>> And it's going to Yeah, it's going to
take your analyst 6 months to to
separate the wheat from the chaff. And
by then, the next bomb has gone off, the
next operation has taken place, and it's
just too late. Besides the fact that
it's illegal,
>> how much time did you do in prison for
this, John?
23 months.
>> Tell me about that if you would.
>> Yeah. At sentencing, I was sentenced in
the Eastern District of Virginia, uh,
which is also known as the Espionage
Court because it's the the home district
of the CIA, of the Pentagon, of the
Department of Homeland Security, and
countless intelligence and defense
contractors.
So my attorneys asked the sentencing
judge to send me to a minimum security
work camp. She agreed. The prosecution
had no objection,
but the CIA did. And so in the months
between I was sentenced in October and
when I went to prison in February, they
made sure that I was sent to an actual
prison with the double concertina wire
fences and the armed guards and the, you
know, the big water tower and the whole
nine yards. Um, it took me about four
days to get access to a phone once I got
there. And I called my lead attorney and
I said, "Hey, they put me in the actual
prison with the mafia dons and the drug
kingpins and the pedophiles. What do I
do?"
And he said, "My god, well, we could
file a motion, but it'll be two years
before we get a hearing and you'll be
home by then." He said, "Buddy, I'm
sorry. You're going to have to tough it
out." And so I decided at really at that
moment
that
I was trained for this.
I was going to use my CIA training to
make sure that I remained at the top of
the social heap and kept myself safe.
And so I began by creating strategic
alliances beginning with the Aryans and
the Italians. And um
it was not difficult time.
Uh the the worst part of it is the
monotony. It's just it's Groundhog Day.
Day after day after day,
>> but never had any problems.
>> Did you read? Did you write? How did you
pass the time?
>> Uh yes to both. Uh on the very first day
that I was there, I I had only been in
prison for like four hours and uh there
was mail call and I got a letter from a
lady in Ringold, Georgia.
I didn't know who this woman was, but
she sent me a nice card and there was a
letter inside the card and I thought,
"Wow, that was so nice of this woman, a
complete stranger to me." But she took
time out of her day to tell me good luck
and she's thinking about me. And I I
decided that day that I was going to
respond to every piece of mail that I
got, not realizing I was going to answer
7,000 letters from 675 different people.
>> But I did. I also wrote a book in
Longhand called Doing Time Like a Spy:
How the CIA Taught Me to Survive and
Thrive in Prison. Um that won two
literary awards. I won one of the big
four. I won I won the pen first
amendment award which along with the pen
falner the Pulitzer and the Edgar Alan
Poe is one of the big four literary
prizes and I won the forward reviews
memoir of the year and um and I read
voraciously
uh I was there 23 months I read more
than a hundred books and uh you know
just
counted down the days.
John, what do you say to people from
the, you know, current and former
intelligence community, people that call
you a trader? What do you say to them?
>> Nobody calls me a traitor.
>> No.
>> In all ser in all seriousness, my
detractors are all either dead or
retired.
And this new generation at the agency
acknowledges me as a whistleblower.
Dozens of them have reached out to me
for advice. And listen, I said from the
very beginning, I was on the right side
of history.
>> I agree.
>> The CIA's leader leadership was not. And
it's taken a few years, a decade, but
the agency as a body has come around to
my position as I knew it would.
>> Agreed.
>> John, tell us about the farm. What
surprised you most in your CIA training
that you didn't expect from the movies?
>> Oh. Ah,
none of the movies are accurate. So, I
really I really
>> What's What's the closest?
>> The closest is The Recruit,
>> which came out in like 200
four, 2002 something. Um, good movie.
Aluchccino's in it. Um, the only thing
that they exaggerated was, um, in the
movie they beat him and they didn't beat
us in training. It was hard. It was
physical, but they didn't beat us. That
that film came the closest. Most other
films are nonsense.
>> I was kind of hoping you would say
Sakario.
>> Uh, no, I was okay. But most most CIA
people hate CIA films. I was I was the
script consultant on one. It was a John
Travolta film called uh From Paris with
Love.
>> Okay. And it was so absurd. I was
embarrassed actually to be associated
with it. There was one scene where
Travolta is he's in Paris. He's been
sent out by Langley and he's going
through the streets of of Paris in a
limousine and he's standing
half out of the the sunroof on a
limousine and he's just opening fire
with machine guns in both hands and he's
selling cocaine and you know it's like
come on you guys,
>> right?
>> But most of them are just just awful.
Just awful.
>> Got you. So I certainly remember where I
was. I was I was a new transplant to LA.
Where were you on 911 and what was the
immediate response inside the agency in
the days after?
>> Yeah, I was in I was in headquarters on
911. Um I was uh I Uh-huh. I was uh I
had a 9:00 meeting scheduled with
Condisa Rice. I was going with Kofheer
Black who was the head of the
counterterrorism center and it was on a
very quaint now very specific little
issue related to um Greek terrorism
and uh the driver called me to tell me
that he was ready to pick us up. This
was like 8:15 or 8:10 and um I walked
over to Kofheer's office and these are
the days before you could watch TV on
your computer. So his secretary had a
little TV on her desk and it was on and
one of the towers of the World Trade
Center was burning. And I said, "What
happened to the World Trade Center?" And
she said, "A plane flew into it." And I
said, "You know, that happened once
before in the 1930s. A plane flew into
the Empire State Building, a bomber, but
it it was pouring down rain and it was
foggy then. It's so crystal clear today.
How can you not see that you're flying
into the World Trade Center?" And just
as I spoke the words, the second plane
flew in. And then she turned to me over
her shoulder like this and she said,
"Did you see that or did I imagine it?"
And then it was just kind of a quiet
chaos. [sighs]
We had to be ordered to evacuate.
Everybody evacuated.
Somebody said, "You know, we should
probably assume that one of these planes
is headed here." Nobody wanted to
evacuate. Finally, one of those CIA
policemen, the CIA has its own police
force, um, he came in and said, "If you
don't evacuate, you'll be arrested." So,
everybody evacuated.
I ended up abandoning my car halfway
between headquarters and my apartment
just cuz I couldn't I couldn't make it
any further. I walked the rest of the
way.
I saw the deputy national security
adviser walking. He had crossed the
Teddy Roosevelt bridge and he was
walking and he had no shoes.
And that sticks in my mind as one of the
most significant things of that day.
Like this was really a catastrophe when
the deputy national security adviser of
the United States abandons his office,
runs for his life, and leaves his shoes.
It's
>> crazy.
>> So I went to my my then girlfriend, she
later became my wife, but my girlfriend
and I went to the roof of my building.
We watched the Pentagon burn for a
little while and um I said we should try
to we should try to donate blood or
something, but the lines were so long.
It was like a 20 22 24-hour line. And
finally I said, "This is ridiculous. We
we got to get back to work." She was
also a CIA officer. And so we walked
back to my car,
drove across the median back to
headquarters, and then I stayed there
for the next 4 days.
Well, you became chief of
counterterrorist operations in Pakistan
almost immediately after 9/11. How
quickly did that happen and what was the
mandate at the time?
>> Well, that's that's a good question.
Like everybody in the building, I just
kept volunteering, constantly
volunteering. You got to send me to
Afghanistan. You got to send me to
Afghanistan. I was one of the few people
who spoke fluent Arabic at the time, and
I figured, who's interrogating these
people? You got to send me to
Afghanistan. And then I ran into a
colleague in the hall who I hadn't seen
in six weeks and I said, "Where have you
been?" And he says, "Afghanistan." I
said, "Yeah, what are you doing in
Afghanistan?" He said, "I'm killing
people. What do you think I'm doing?"
And then I it dawned on me, "They don't
need interrogators. They don't need
linguists. They're just killing people."
So I angrily went into the deputy
director of counterterrorism. I went
into his office. I said, "Look," he he
and I were old friends. I said, "If you
don't send me to Afghanistan right now,
I'm going to walk straight to Exxon with
my Arabic, and I'm not looking back."
He's like, "All right, all right, take
it easy. Can you be uh chief of uh
counterterrorism offic?" I said, "Yes.
When?" He said, "Tomorrow." I said,
"Yes." "How long do you want me to go?"
I said, he said, "I I don't know, as
long as it needs to be." So the next day
I got in the plane and flew to Pakistan
and I had no idea if this was going to
be 6 months, 9 months, 12 months, no
idea.
>> What was your state of mind? Was it
blind rage rage or anger or just
pragmatism?
>> It was it was anger. And I can't tell
you how many people kind of whispered to
me, "Kill them all."
>> As I was getting ready to leave. Um,
but then once I arrived, pragmatism set
in because it's not just like they're
they're not just like carrying
membership cards that say al-Qaeda.
>> Yeah. And they're not in uniforms. Yeah.
>> Right. They're not in uniforms. You got
to you have to find them. You have to
hunt them. And so the chase was on. I
came up with a couple of ideas that I
was very proud of. You know, rather than
guard the border, just pull everybody
off the border. let them come in cuz
they're going to seek out a safe house
with other Arabs. They're going to make
a mistake. They always do, whether it's
by using a cell phone or going into an
email account or, you know, speaking to
the wrong person in the marketplace,
whatever. And then we'll be able to
catch a bunch of them at once rather
than one or two at a time on the border.
And that ended up working very well.
What would you estimate the the the
climate of Islamist sleeper cells to be
like in 2025? And how are we watching
them?
>> I'm going to answer that question with a
with a story,
>> please.
After we caught up, about a week after
we caught up,
um I drove up to Pashau with a guy from
the embassy. He was actually a detective
from the Port Authority of New York and
New Jersey police department and he was
on loan to the FBI. Awesome guy named
Tommy McCale. So Tommy and I went up to
Pashauer to do this little thing. And on
the way back, it was night. It was like
10 or 11 at night. We drove past the
only remaining and functioning Taliban
embassy in the world. And he said, he
said, "Look at this. They have such
nerve, these guys
still having a functioning embassy."
And he said,
"We should go in there and we should
steal everything that's not bolted to
the floor." And I laughed and I said,
"Yeah, that would be awesome." And then
I thought, "No, you know what? That's
exactly what we should do. That's
exactly what we should do." went back to
head went back to the embassy and I sent
a cable to headquarters request
permission to raid the Taliban embassy
in the middle of the night and steal
everything.
And the next day they said permission
granted. So we put a team together. We
requisitioned three vans from the
embassy motor. We drove up 2:00 a.m. We
busted down the door and we stole
literally everything in that building.
computers, cell phones, paper files. We
filled almost all three of the vans with
paper files.
>> Wow.
>> So, we took everything back back to the
embassy. We had to store it in the
hallways. There was so much stuff.
And then the FBI had flown in a a group
of computer uh people to just, you know,
mirror image all of the the uh hard
>> drives. Yeah. Anyway, about about five
or six days later, Tommy comes up to my
office and he says, "Hey, something
disturbing
uh is in these files. We just found it."
I went downstairs and it was a file
folder of telephone bills, all in
English, and they showed dozens upon
dozens of calls from the Taliban embassy
to numbers all across the United States,
Buffalo, New York. Bethesda, Maryland,
Kansas City, um, uh, Estus Park, uh,
Colorado, all across America. And then
they abruptly stopped on September 10th,
and then they slowly started up again on
September 16th.
So I cabled headquarters. I said, "Be
advised. We just found this file folder,
etc., etc." They said, "Good catch. Make
sure that the FBI gets the originals.
send copies to us and give copies to the
packs. So that's what we did
with the idea being there appear to be
or at least there appears to be the
possibility of sleeper cells all across
America.
>> So um
>> they never they never looked at the
files. They never opened the box. And
when I finally asked an FBI agent two
years later, "What about all those those
phone bills?" He said, "Yeah, you know
what? We couldn't find a Poshtu
translator." I said, "They were in
English. That's how I knew they were
phone bills. I'm I don't speak Poshtu."
And so, nothing was ever done with those
files. We have no idea if if they had
been indicating sleeper cells. And then,
uh, a little while later, after I got
back to the United States, um, in the
late spring, I was up in New York with a
carload of FBI agents. We were driving
down First Avenue and um and one of them
pointed a pointed at a um a storefront
and he said, "You see that storefront?
That's the headquarters of Hezbollah in
New York. Very dangerous." I said,
"Well, then why the fuck don't you raid
it and grab everybody if they're so
dangerous? What's the matter with you
guys?"
>> Yeah.
>> So, the answer to your question is we
don't have any idea how many sleeper
cells there are. There are a bunch. I'll
tell you that. The FBI just arrested a
group of them a few days ago uh in the
Inland Empire in the California desert.
But is it because there is just one or
are there five or 10 or a hundred? We
don't have any idea.
>> Well, I think I think we're going to
have to get get uh uh
get get up to snuff pretty quickly with
uh with what's going on in the world.
>> So, let me ask you something. Is
Islamism rising, stabilizing, or
winning? It's not looking good here or
in Europe.
>> I think it's more um amorphous
uh than it it seems. Um it is certainly
on the Wayne in places like the Levant
for example or even Afghanistan,
but it's certainly on the upswing in the
Sahel uh in parts of East Asia like like
the southern Philippines for example.
Syria is very dangerous. Sudan is very
dangerous. Somalia will always be
dangerous. So, it just kind of es and
flows and moves.
It's almost like playing whack-a-ole.
Sure, you're going to you're going to
stomp one out and then another one's
going to pop up somewhere else.
>> Yeah. I mean, what I'm most concerned
about is what's happening here uh from
sea to shining sea.
>> What do you think the horizon looks
like?
I think we're always going to be under
threat here because that's sort of the
crown jewel of terrorism, isn't it?
>> Yeah.
>> To carry out a terrorist attack in the
United States.
>> Mhm. [sighs]
>> So, h how do you think the agencies are
working now?
>> Oh, we know that the agencies are
working far far better together, far
more closely together. It wasn't until
that the CIA and FBI computer systems
were compatible with one another.
>> Really,
>> that's that's how deep the animosity
was. That's how that's how difficult the
institutional relationships were. It
took eight years after the 9/11 attacks
just for the computers to be able to
send messages to one another.
>> Wow.
>> Let me ask you this. Do you think it's
too late for Europe?
That's that's a tough one. Um,
in some ways, parts of Western Europe.
Yeah. Um, the French sort of invited it
by colonizing Algeria and then through
bad military decisions radicalizing the
population.
Um, the Brits, same thing. You know,
when you're a colonial power and then
you spin your your colonies off, you
sort of have to let them come in if they
want to come in. They are British
subjects.
>> Yeah.
>> And so, um,
you know, and even some of the countries
that take refugees like the Netherlands
for example or Denmark or even Sweden,
parted Sweden.
>> Yeah. especially in the south of Sweden,
they're they're the Swedes have
generally gotten it right. immigration
and and and the influx of refugees
um have pushed the Swedish electorate to
the right, but the Swedes have made good
use of ethnic Arab um refugees, Swedish
citizens who become police officers and
then are able to liaz with the refugee
communities in Arabic or Pashto or Udo
or whatever and keep things peaceful.
The Brits and the French haven't had
that good fortune.
>> What role does social media play in
terrorism and counterterrorism now?
>> Oh, I think social media plays an
increasingly sophisticated role in
terrorism. you know, going back to the
San Bernardino attacks uh several years
ago, they were communicating with each
other through gaming systems and social
media, uh in in the the fantastic
Israeli uh Netflix series FA
um in the final season, they only
communicated with each other
operationally
through gaming systems and social media.
>> That was
>> and they did that because that's
fascinating. Listen, if any of your
listeners are interested in a in a show
that can't possibly be any closer to
reality, it's that one.
>> I love I love that show.
>> Me, too.
Me, too.
>> So, uh yeah, I I've heard mixed uh
opinions from you on working with
Mossad, but uh explain to me what it was
like.
>> Yeah, I'm not sure my opinions are
really that mixed. Um, they are probably
the best intelligence service in the
world. I'll give them that. But they
actively and aggressively spy on the
United States. Uh, they are spread out
all across the country trying trying to
steal defense secrets, trying to recruit
Americans and um and are sometimes
successful.
and um they they just don't treat, you
know, on a day-to-day basis, they don't
treat CIA officers that they're supposed
to be working with and liazing with
respect. And so, as a result, I can
honestly tell you that in all my years
at the CIA, I never met anybody who
enjoyed working with the Israelis.
Not a person.
>> Got you. So, back to whistleblowers for
a moment. It just occurs to me. So, I'm
curious where you think the line is. Um,
Julian Assange, Edward Snowden, heroes
or villains?
>> Oh, I think both heroes. Um, the there's
a legal definition of whistleblowing in
the United States. It's bringing to
light any evidence of waste, fraud,
abuse, illegality, or threats to the
public health or public safety. And
motivation is irrelevant in the law.
So, waste, fraud, abuse, or threats to
the illegality or threats to the public
health or public safety. Um,
I wouldn't have gone about it the way Ed
and Julian did, but what they did was to
reveal crimes and so I think that they
performed a public service. Besides the
fact that Julian's not even an American
citizen, so charging him like accusing
him of treason, like treason, he's not
an American. That's not treason.
>> I always thought that was kind of silly.
>> It's like, you committed treason against
the Germans. Well, I'm not German, so I
don't care.
Let me ask you this. What What if the
West continues to prioritize moral
performance over survival?
I I I think the whole basis of that
question is wrong. It It doesn't have to
be an eitheror proposition.
No, you don't have to be an outlaw to
protect your country. We have laws for a
reason. And listen, if you want to
torture people, God bless. Change the
law and say, "Listen, I like torture. I
want to torture people. So, I want the
law to say I can torture people." Just
be honest about it.
>> It's as simple as that. But at the same
time, you can't be this shining city on
a hill like Ronald Reagan said, this
shining beacon of hope for human rights
and civil rights and civil liberties.
Like, don't don't yank people's chains
like that. Just be what you want to be.
And if you want to be the country that
tortures people because you think it's
going to make you safer, then be that
country.
>> What does make us safer?
>> Good intelligence.
treating people with respect even when
we disagree with them, even when they're
not here in the United States. Treating
people, treating countries equally with
respect. One of the things that I
learned very quickly when I was in
Pakistan was that
among these young al-Qaeda fighters,
they all told essentially the same
story. They said that they were from
isolated villages in their country. They
were illiterate. They had no job
training, like nothing. They could
barely tie their own shoes. And they
wanted to get married. They're 18, 19
years old. They want to get married. And
they couldn't get married because no man
would want his daughter to marry a guy
who can't read, can't write, has no job
skills, no future, and he lives in a
village with 50 people.
So the local imam said to them, "You
don't want to stay in this village. You
should go to Afghanistan and make jihad
against the Americans and we'll pay you
$300 a month. And if you're martyed,
we'll give your parents a $500 martyrdom
bonus."
>> Christ.
>> And they said fine, cuz they had nothing
better going on. They couldn't find the
United States on a map,
>> right?
>> And they had never read the Quran. So
they didn't do this for religious
purposes. They did it because their
lives were so dire that they had nothing
else. And so economic development and
education are the two greatest weapons
against terrorism.
Now we're in a political situation now
in the in the United States where we
don't want to have anything that calls
itself foreign aid. Right? And so we're
stuck in this in this loop now where,
you know, we're going to have to keep
fighting them in these battlefield
countries because we don't want to help
develop their economies and, you know,
and their education systems.
It's tricky. [clears throat]
What made you to decide to go on ABC
News in 2007 and and and do that
whistleblowing?
Brian Ross from ABC News called me and
told me that he had a source who said
that I had tortured Abu Zuba. I said it
was absolutely untrue. I was the only
person who was kind to Abu Zuba. And he
said, "Well, you can come on and defend
yourself." I had no idea that was a
reporter's trick. Um but then the
president said twice that next week, he
said that there was no torture. He we do
not torture. He said,
>> I remember.
>> And the second thing is he alluded to
the notion that
>> there was there was torture, but it was
because of a rogue CIA officer and that
they were going to blame me.
>> And so I decided I'm going to go on and
I'm just going to tell the truth and I
exposed the program.
>> So how how was it first teed up to you
before you rejected the the concept of
enhanced interrogation?
Oh, I was standing in the cafeteria in
line and uh and a colleague of mine, a
senior officer from the counterterrorism
center came up to me very casually and
said, "Oh," he goes, "Hey, I'm glad I
ran into you. Do you want to be
certified in the use of enhanced
interrogation techniques?" I had never
heard that term before. I said, "What's
that mean, enhanced interrogation
techniques?" And he said, "Uh, we're
going to start getting rough with these
guys." I said, "Well, what does that
mean?" And then he explained these
techniques. I said, 'Th that sounds like
a torture program. He said, 'It's not a
torture program. DOJ approved it and the
president signed it. I said, I don't
know. Let me let me think about it for
an hour. Well, I went to the seventh
floor, the executive floor of the CIA.
There was a very senior, very, very
senior officer there for whom I had
worked in the Middle East 10 years
earlier. And I asked his advice. He
said, "Don't do it."
So I went back downstairs. I said, "This
is a torture program. I have a moral and
ethical problem with it. I think it's
illegal on top of it. I don't want any
part of it." And so they they had
actually approached 14 people and I was
the only one who said no.
What's the most important thing people
don't understand about what you actually
went to prison for?
>> You know, I uh I was convicted of
violating the Intelligence Identities
Protection Act of 1981. I confirmed the
surname of a former colleague, a retired
colleague. Um, the surname was never
made public. Never. Nobody knows what
the name was. Um, and people think that
that's why I got prosecuted. Well, David
Petraeus, when he was director of the
CIA, revealed the names of 10 covert CIA
operatives. He wasn't even charged. And
Leon Panetta, the names of six covert
operatives. He was never charged. So
people say, "Well, you revealed
somebody's name." Really? What was the
name if I revealed it? What was that
name? Oh, you don't know? Because nobody
knows it was never revealed.
>> Right.
>> So people people need to understand that
>> I was punished for blowing the whistle
on the CIA's torture program. That was
my punishment. And they just scoured
>> Yeah. They just scoured the law books
looking for something to charge me with.
And that was the hook that they found. I
read, I don't know if it's true or not,
but I read that you were told that you
could get a Trump pardon for $2 million.
Is that true? And if so, did it come
about? And how did you respond?
>> Well, no, of course it didn't come
about. I haven't worked in 10 years
except myself.
>> I know.
>> No, it was And that was on the front
page of the New York Times. Rudy
Giuliani tried to shake me down for $2
million.
>> Really? That
>> Oh, yeah.
>> Tell me Tell me how that happened.
>> I was one of six people. Yeah. So,
a friend of mine said, "Hey, Giuliani,
you know, Giuliani is so close to Trump.
This is way back in in 2020.
Uh, Giuliani is really close to Trump.
You should try to get to Giuliani." And
I said, "Well, I I I do have one path to
Giuliani."
So, I called this friend of mine and I
said, "Hey, can you connect me with
Giuliani?" And he said, "Yeah."
So, um, so he did uh with one of
Giuliani's aids. And um I told him what
I was looking for and he said,
"Actually, we're going to be in
Washington on Tuesday. Why don't we get
together for a drink at the Trump
Hotel?" So we did, we got together. I
was with my attorney and um and we're
sitting there and I said, you know, so
nice to meet you. You know, we shook
hands and and then Giuliani is like, um,
you like the Giants, New York Giants?
And I said, oh, um I'm a Steelers fan.
I'm originally from Western
Pennsylvania, but sure. Yeah, the Giants
are great. Uh, Mets or Yankees? He says
to me. I said, "Oh, Pirates, actually,
as bad as they are. I love the Pirates.
Always have." And finally, I said, "Mr.
Mayor, there's this issue of a pardon I
wanted to discuss with you." And he
says, "Well," and he stands up. He says,
"Anybody know where the pisser is?" And
he just walks away.
>> It's crazy.
>> Okay.
>> I said to the aid, I said, "What what
just happened?" And he says, "You never
talk to Rudy about the pardon. You talk
to me about the pardon." And I talked to
Rudy.
>> I was like, "Okay, whatever."
>> Good fellas. Yeah.
>> So, yeah. So, uh, he says, "Rudy's going
to want$2 million." And I laughed. I
looked at my lawyer. We both laughed. I
said, "Listen, first of all, I don't
have $2 million. I'll never have $2
million."
>> Yeah. But secondly, why in the world
would I spend $2 million to recover a
$700,000 pension? So I stood up. I said,
"Thanks for your time." And we walked
out. That night, I went to a book launch
event um on Capitol Hill. Buddy of mine
was coming out with a book and I ran
into another whistleblower, TSA
whistleblower, and he said to me, "How
was your day?" And I said, "Oh, listen
to how my day was. Let me tell you what
I did today. So, I told him the story
that I just told you and he says,
"That's a felony." I said, "I know it's
a felony. They came right out and asked
me for it." And he said, "Did you call
the FBI?" And I said, "Come on, man. The
FBI doesn't give a shit about stuff like
this."
So, a week passes and I happened to be
in my lawyer's office. I was standing
next to him and my cell phone rings and
it's Mike Schmidt from the New York
Times and he says, "A little bird told
me that Rudy Giuliani tried to shake you
down for 2 million for a pardon." And I
said, "Ah, that Bob." I said, "Yeah, Bob
was really upset when I told him the
story." And he said, "Well, has the FBI
called you?" And I said, "No." And he
said, "Well, Bob called the FBI and he
reported this as a crime." I said, "God
bless him." I I kind of I kind of
thought that he would. And um he said,
"The FBI hasn't called you." And I said,
"Nope." He said, "Well, you're the sixth
person that we've identified
um who was pitched by Giuliani for a
bribe to to get them a pardon. Would you
be willing to go on the record?" So I
said, "Hold on." I said to my lawyer,
"Am I willing to go on the record?" And
he says, "Go on the record." So I said,
"Sure, I'll go on the record." And uh
and I gave him the interview. And I I
told him exactly the same story that I
just told you. So
I was heartened
when two years later, Noel Duny, who
used to be uh the head of business
development for Giuliani Partners, told
me that when the New York Times article
came out,
Giuliani said that fucking Kuryaku
ratted me out.
>> I loved it. But what happened was
killed. Yeah.
>> When the Times called him, he said,
"I've never met this man. I've never
heard of this man. The meeting never
took place." So, they wanted my comment.
And I said, "Oh my god, he forgot that
we took a picture together."
So, I sent them the picture. And so, he
had his denial,
categorical denial. And then underneath
it said, "The New York Times has seen
documentary evidence that the meeting
took place."
Something about that guy. You throw him
out of an airplane and he goes up.
>> Who can figure it out? I don't
understand. The guy's got nine lives.
>> I don't know.
>> Yeah. If you would uh jumping over, uh
I' I I'd love to I've heard a bit of it
before. I'd love to hear uh about the
history of the kill list.
>> Well, this is something that even I
didn't know about. I had left the agency
in 2004. My resignation was effective in
2005. And I was up on the Senate Foreign
Relations Committee staff when um when a
journalist from the Boston Globe called
me and said that there was going to be a
a feature story in the New Yorker about
the Tuesday morning kill list. I said,
"I don't know what you're talking
about." And she said, 'It's this meeting
that John Brennan has at the White House
every Tuesday morning at 7 a.m. He meets
with a gaggle of lawyers and CIA
operational people and they draw up a
list of who to kill that week and they
come up with the list. They agree on the
list. The president signs it and then
these teams fan out across the country
and kill people who are on the list and
then they meet up again the next
Tuesday.
>> Just domestically or or abroad is
>> No, no, no, no. All All abroad. You
can't kill people domestically.
>> I didn't I didn't think so. Okay.
>> We have murder. That's murder. Yeah. You
can't do that here.
>> Yeah. I mean, theoretically, you could
according to Barack Obama's rules of
engagement.
>> Yeah. I wanted I wanted to Yeah. Go
ahead. I wanted to talk to you about
that. I wanted I wanted to see what the
what what the moral uh equivalent was,
you know, or the moral distinction
between the drone program and enhanced
interrogation.
>> I mean, that's really the $64,000
question. Um
the the DNI at the time, uh Jim Clapper,
>> yeah,
>> was testifying before the Senate Armed
Services Committee at the end of the
Obama presidency.
And Ran Paul, Senator Ran Paul, the
Republican of Kentucky, asked him
pointedly multiple times if, according
to the Obama administration's rules of
engagement, the president was allowed
legally to use a drone to kill someone
in the United States who had never been
formally accused of a crime. And there
was hemming and hawing and, you know,
double speak. And then finally, yeah,
the answer is yes. Yes. Now, we don't
know if that's ever happened. They say
it hasn't, and I guess they just want us
to take their word for it. But Barack
Obama was far, far deadlier than George
W. Bush ever was. Far deadlier. He
killed 10 times the number of people
with drones than George W. Bush did and
had no compunction
uh about targeting Americans. Anoir
Alalaki, who was the spokesman for
al-Qaeda, was an American citizen. He
was born in in uh Albuquerque, New
Mexico,
>> and Obama killed him and then a week
later killed his 16-year-old American
citizen son and 16-year-old American
citizen nephew who were just sitting in
a coffee shop
just because.
What's your What's your re take on
what's really going on in Venezuela?
I think that there are elements of the
Bush administration that adhere to that
tired old neoonservative ideology.
Um they have convinced the president
that Venezuela is a major drug problem
for us. It is not. It never has been.
There are drugs going through Venezuela,
but they are going through Venezuela on
their way to West Africa for trans
shshipment to Western Europe. They are
not bound for the United States. We have
a far far bigger problem with Mexico,
Colombia, and Ecuador than we ever have
had with drugs in uh Venezuela. But I
think that that this is really being
I think that the real motivator behind
the policy is Marco Rubio.
I think that he wants Maduro gone. There
are 20 different,
you know, proposed operations for making
Maduro go and we'll just see which one
they finally implement.
>> Do you think we have a lot of assets in
Mexico? Speaking of the cartel and and
how how does that get sorted out?
>> No, I don't think we have many assets in
Mexico. I would be surprised if we had
any real assets in Mexico because
>> because until a year ago, this was DEA's
problem. Uh if you're a Netflix viewer,
I'm sure you saw the series Narcos.
>> Yeah. You know, and every season,
whether they're going after Pablo
Escobar or the gentleman of Kali or one
of the Mexican cartels, just as they're
going in for the big raid, the CIA
station chief steps in and fucks
everything up. And the reason that they
do that season after season is because
that's what it's like in real life. The
CIA doesn't care about drugs. Drugs are
not the CIA's problem. That's DEA's
problem. The CIA is concerned about
communism and terrorism,
not drugs. And so sometimes it's to the
CIA's benefit to to work with the drug
cartels if they're going to tell us
where the communists are.
>> Well, you've certainly dealt with plenty
of drugs in the history of the CIA, but
isn't um
aren't the cartels terrorists and drug
dealers?
>> No.
>> There's a definition of terrorism.
Yeah, it's it's using violence against
the public for the purpose of instilling
widespread terror.
So, no. Okay.
>> I don't I don't think this the Caloa
cartel isn't sending cells in here to
blow up schools and, you know, bridges
or attack shopping malls. That's
terrorism.
So, no, I think they're they're drug
kingpins.
you know, which is a death penalty
offense in and of itself, but I I don't
think they're terrorists. No.
>> Yeah. You've said in the past that you
feel very strongly that Jeffrey Epstein
was a MSAD access agent. Walk us through
that and what's your evidence?
>> Yeah. Uh this is a textbook um access
agent. So if you're a if you're a
foreign intelligence service and you
want intelligence from very very highly
placed people like a former president,
like the founder of the one of the
biggest companies in the world, like a
top member of the British royal family,
you're not going to recruit those
people. So you do the next best thing.
You recruit somebody who has access to
them.
>> Sure. and and maybe you compromise them
a little bit by offering up, you know,
underage girls or some blow or whatever.
You put them in compromising positions.
You videotape everything with hidden
cameras all over your mansion and then
you get the information that your your
handler wants.
>> Sure. But couldn't have Epstein just
done that on his of his own valition
just for extortion and influence and
power on his own.
>> But there's no evidence that he extorted
anybody.
I mean, you got to do something with the
influence. You got to do something with
the power. You can't just sit on it like
an egg.
>> Well, where did And where did his money
come from? That this guy never went to
college.
>> I That's the thing. That's the thing.
You know, some say Leslie Wexner. Uh but
but but there there's very little
evidence of him ever even having a job.
>> Exactly.
>> Yeah.
>> That money had to come from somewhere.
Um Yeah. I've always felt that it was
compromat on other people. And I knew
and I knew a lot of people who went
through Epstein's various events. And
the thing that most people don't
understand that I want to be clear about
is there was a period of time that
everybody at a certain social station in
life ended up at an Epstein party. That
didn't make them a pedophile any more
than That's right. the thousands of
people I know that went to diddy parties
here in LA and did not know about
Freakoff. So I I I
>> It's like the plane like people said,
"Oh, Robert Kennedy Jr. was on the
plane." Yeah. With his wife and his
children.
>> That's right. They h they had a
conversation one time. What are you
going to do for Easter? We're going to
go to Palm Beach. Oh, I'm going to go to
Palm Beach for Easter. Why don't you
come on my plane? And he gave them a
ride. And that was it. So, yeah, sure.
RFK Jr. was on the plane. So was his
entire family. No big deal.
>> Yeah. And I had heard from someone that
was at the island a lot that said every
time Bill Clinton came to the island,
the girls were cleared out.
>> Okay, that's a good thing.
>> Yeah. And in fact, nobody has accused
Bill Clinton of improper behavior with
underage girls.
>> Correct.
So, you've known John Brennan since
1990, and you worked for him twice. Why
did you call him a terrible choice to
lead the CIA at the time?
>> I never thought John was particularly
intelligent. I thought that uh he
achieved his high rank because he was
very personally close to George Tennant.
They hit it off. They were great
friends. And every time uh George had
the opportunity to promote John, he
promoted him. But I never thought he was
particularly bright. And as it turned
out, he was also vicious beyond
anything I had ever seen ever in my
adult life before or after.
Interesting. Do you think American
exceptionalism, the idea that we're
better than other countries, is real, or
is it just propaganda?
Oh yeah. I mean it's it's real in the
minds of a lot of people.
>> Sure.
>> But uh and I used to think I used to
believe in American exceptionalism. I
really did until I saw how the sausage
got made and then I realized no, we're
just as flawed as everybody else.
Yeah. the uh the Obama administration,
which you're no fan of, prosecuted more
whistleblowers under the Espionage Act
than all previous presidents combined.
Why?
>> That's right. Three times as many as all
previous presidents combined. That
That's an easy answer. Actually, it's
because John Brennan was in charge of
those uh of those cases. He instilled in
Barack Obama a Nixonian obsession with
national security leaks and convinced
Obama to go after people with the full
force of the Justice Department. I mean,
we got we got memos in Discovery in my
own case. I'm sure you've heard me say
this in the past where Brennan writes to
uh writes to Eric Holder, the attorney
general, and says, "Charge him with
espionage." And Holder writes back and
says, "My people don't think he
committed espionage." And then Brennan
writes back to Holder and says, "Charge
him anyway and make him defend himself."
They charged me with three counts of
espionage, waited until I went bankrupt,
and then dropped the espionage charges.
>> And now it's Brennan's turn to get that
kind of treatment.
>> Yeah. John,
>> what you sow?
>> Yeah. John, if a young person came to
you today telling you they wanted to
join CIA, what would you tell them?
depends on what day it is to tell you
the truth. Um like deep down I I think
the CIA should be abolished
but
>> replaced with what?
>> It's already there are 18 intelligence
agencies in the US government. It's
already replaced by 17 others. You don't
even need to create anything else. The
the State Department has the Bureau of
Intelligence and Research that does
analysis that is at least as good as the
CIA's analysis and in many ways better.
The Pentagon's Defense Human Services
already recruits spies to steal secrets
just like the CIA does. We don't need
the DO to do that. The director of
operations, DARPA and NSA already do all
the science and technology stuff as well
as the the public se or sorry the
private sector doing it thanks to you
know investments from INQEL. I mean look
at Palanteer. It's a CIA creation.
>> Yeah. So, what does the CIA do that's
unique or particularly valuable?
Nothing. Now, with that said, I'm a
realist and I know that the CIA is not
going to be disbanded. And so I tell
people if you want to get into the CIA,
go in with your own set of moral
principles, moral values, and by the
time you're in for about 10 years,
you're you're in a position of some
authority by then, and you might be able
to change the organization from inside,
but other than that, I I I wish it would
just fall apart.
>> Got your two more questions. Do you have
any regrets about the way you handle
things or would you do it all again the
same way?
>> I would do it all again. But the there
is one important thing I would change
and I say this to to wouldbe
whistleblowers all the time. Have an
attorney sitting next to you. Uh go to
an attorney, especially an attorney
who's skilled in whistleblower
protection before you blow the whistle.
Don't be reactive like I was.
>> Got you. Uh what are you working on now?
And what's next for John Keryaku?
>> I'm doing a lot right now. I have three,
thank God, I have three successful
podcasts on on Rumble and YouTube. I
have one every day called Deep Program.
On YouTube, I have one that's like crazy
successful. I can't even believe it.
Called Deep Focus with John Kuryaku.
I've got one on uh Apple uh podcast on
Spotify called John Kuryaku's
um John Kuryaku's uh dead drop. What
makes a spy tick? It's in the top 2% of
all podcasts worldwide now. And I've
been able, thank God, to monetize them
all. I just sent my
um my ninth book to the publisher. My
eighth book is coming out March 20 24th.
It's called uh Remains of the Day, a
definitive guide to Washington DC's
Historic Cemeteries. It's my eighth
book, but my first one that's not about
the CIA. My next one um
>> is called uh Whispers in the Dirt, a
definitive guide to New York City's
Mafia Graves. And um
>> yeah, and I'm teaching at a couple of
different universities. And there's
there's a lot going on. John, what's the
best place for my listeners to uh to
catch up with you and find all your
links?
>> Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. It's uh
easy. It's johnkuryaku.com.
john i r i a k o.com.
>> Great. Appreciate it.
>> Thanks so much for taking all the time
with me and answering all the questions.
>> My pleasure. Good to see you.
>> You too. The Bad Decisions podcast was
produced by Brock Workman of Herat
Entertainment. Be sure to hit the like
button [music] and subscribe to the show
on YouTube, Spotify, Apple, or wherever
you get your podcasts. My book, The Big
Book [music] of Bad Decisions, is
available for purchase wherever books
are sold. A special thanks to today's
guest, John Kuryaku, for joining me. I'm
your host, Scott Nathan. Thanks for
listening.